Finding Aid for Murray D. Van Wagoner Papers 1921-1949
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Murray D. Van Wagoner Papers 1921-1949
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Construction engineer and Michigan Democratic politician; served terms as Oakland County Drain Commissioner, Michigan State Highway Commissioner, and as Governor, 1941-1942; include correspondence, scrapbooks, appointment books, and assorted miscellanea.
86176 Aa 2; AC
4 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
10 film reels
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Murray D. Van Wagoner (donor no. 4723 ) and came to the library in 1969.
The collection is open for research.
Murray D. Van Wagoner was born March 18, 1898 in Tuscola County, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan College of Engineering in 1921 then went to work for the state highway department where he helped to build bridges. Van Wagoner next went to work for a private engineering company then started his own business.
In the late 1920s, Van Wagoner became interested in elective office. In 1930 he was elected Oakland County drain commissioner, then in 1933, he was elected state highway commissioner. A successful state road building, Van Wagoner was reelected all the while building a political base from which to run for higher office.
In 1940, Van Wagoner was elected Democratic governor of Michigan. As governor during the first two years of the second world war, Van Wagoner was successful in passing many measures related to civil defense and war preparedness. He was largely unsuccessful with his other proposals being opposed by a Republican legislature. He was defeated for re-election in 1942. He ran again in 1946, but was defeated. For the next decades of his life, Van Wagoner worked in private business. He died June 13, 1986.
The series in the Van Wagoner collection are Correspondence (1933-1945); Newspaper clippings/Scrapbooks (1930-1933 and 1940-1949); Miscellaneous/Political; and Visual Materials. The collection is largely an accumulation of personal materials from his career as a public service. There is very little of these papers that might be classified as administrative or office files from his years as highway commissioner or his term as governor.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1930.; Elections--Michigan--1932.; Elections--Michigan--1940.; Elections--Michigan--1942.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Roads--Michigan.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Blue Water Bridge (Port Huron, Mich. and Sarnia, Ont.); Boat and ship industry.; Boats.; Bridges.; Cagney, James, 1899-1986.; Clinton County (Mich.); Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Construction industry.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Defense industry.; Detroit River (Mich. and Ont.); Detroit Tigers (Baseball team); Eaton County (Mich.); Ellington, Duke, 1899-1974.; Europe.; Governors--Michigan--Inauguration--1937.; Governors--Michigan.; Grayling (Mich.); Ingham County (Mich.); Ionia County (Mich.); Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Marine City (Mich.); Mexico.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Parades and processions.; Politics and government--1939-1945.; Railroads--Michigan.; Regattas.; Roads--Michigan.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Swimming.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Veterans--Michigan.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; West (U.S.); Western Michigan University.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Winter.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; De Kruif, Paul, 1890-1971.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-1988; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Murphy, George, 1897-1961.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Scholle, August, 1904-; Tufty, Esther Van Wagoner, d. 1986.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Contributors - Visual Materials
Williams, Frank.
Genre/Form:
Editorial cartoons.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1933-1945, 21 folders (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings/ Scrapbooks
  - Undated 1940-1949, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks 1930-1933 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbooks 1930-1933 (Volume 2)
    (continued)
- Miscellaneous/Political
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook containing in part articles written by Esther Van Wagoner Tufty 1948 (Box 2)
  - Appointment book 1941 (Box 2)
  - Appointment book 1942 (Box 2)
  - Desk diary 1942 (Box 2)
  - Schedule book for Governor Van Wagoner and G. Donald Kennedy 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Notebook of Van Wagoner supporters
    - Alcoma-Huron County (Box 2)
    - Ingham-Oceana County (Box 2)
    - Ogemaw-Wexford County (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  Of most interest is the visual component of the collection - photographs, editorial cartoons, and motion pictures. The photographs are of bridges and roads in Clinton, Eaton, Ingham, and Ionia Counties, Marine City, and Sault Ste. Marie. There are also photographs of political activities and campaigning, and visits to defense plants during World War II. The editorial cartoons are originals, most of which were drawn by Detroit News artist Frank Williams.
  - Photographs
    - Highway Department engineer (1921-1924)
      - Album (Box 2)
        (includes photos of roads and bridges in Clinton, Eaton, Ingham, and Ionia Counties, and bridge construction in Marine City)
      - Loose photos from album (Box 2)
    - Highway Commissioner (1933-1940)
      - Dedications (Box 2)
        (includes photos of Mortimer Cooley)
      - Meetings and office photos (Box 2)
      - Road construction and inspection (Box 2)
        (includes photos of Sault Ste. Marie bridge and automobile riding on railroad tracks; see also box 3)
    - Governor (1941-1942)
      - Defense plant visits
        - Chrysler Tank Arsenal, Dachel Carter Co., and Murray Corp. (Box 2)
          (includes photos of Franklin Roosevelt visit and shipbuilding)
        - Ford Airport and Willow Run Bomber Plant (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Inauguration (Box 2)
      - Mackinac Island (Box 2)
      - Meetings
        - Large groups (Box 2)
          (see also box 3)
        - Small groups (Box 2)
      - Office photos (Box 2)
      - Presentations and visits (Box 2)
        (includes photographs of Van Wagoner with James Cagney and Duke Ellington)
    - Director of Military Government, Bavaria (1947-1948)
      - Individual photos (Box 2)
      - Album (Box 2)
    - Later activities (Box 2)
    - Family photos (Box 2)
    - Political campaigns (Box 2)
      (includes photographs of Franklin Roosevelt and Henry Wallace)
    - Portraits (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 2)
      (see also negative, nc 181, of Van Wagoner speaking at a rally; also include detailed notes on film that have been digitized)
    - Oversized Photographs (Box 3)
      contents listed above
  - Editorial cartoons, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Motion pictures
    The films are of Michigan political figures and of various events, including inaugurations of governors and construction and dedication of the Mackinac and Blue Water Bridges, and of Van Wagoner's travels in the West, Europe, and Mexico.
    - "The Blue Water Bridge", includes footage of construction and dedication circa 1938, 86176-100
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w & color, pos, optical, 00:10:53
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-100, flash-flv
    - "Ready on the Home Front Michigan", chiefly a talk by Van Wagoner circa 1942, 86176-120
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, 00:02:40
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-120, flash-flv
    - Inauguration and other ceremonies, includes footage of Civil War veterans 1930s, 86176-121
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w & color, pos, silent, 00:20:15 @ 18 fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-121, flash-flv
    - European trip (reel 1) 1938, 86176-122-1
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:46:22 @ 18fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-122-1, flash-flv
    - European trip, (reel 2) 1938, 86176-123-2
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:34:48 @ 18fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-123-2, flash-flv
    - Miscellaneous state affairs, excursions, and vacations circa 1941, 86176-124
      (includes footage of boating and boat races on the Detroit River, winter sports in Grayling, Detroit Tigers games at Detroit and Lakeland, Florida, and dedication of Waldo Stadium at Western Michigan University)
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w & color, pos, silent, 00:42:53 @ 18fps
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-124, flash-flv
    - "Scenes from My Western Trip, Fall, 1938" 1938, 86176-125
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:44:35 @ 18fps
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-125, flash-flv
    - Mackinac Bridge construction, dedication, and parade; includes footage of G. Mennen Williams, 1956-57, 86176-126
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:22:53 @ 18 fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-126, flash-flv
    - Miscellaneous footage, 86176-127
      (Concerning state officials; includes footage of William Comstock, 1934 World Series, swimming, winter sports in Grayling, 1937 inauguration of Frank Murphy, and G. Mennen Williams, 1933-38 & 1948)
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w & color, pos, silent, 00:32:08
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-127, flash-flv
    - Inspection trip on Pan American Highway; travel footage of trips to Mexico, western US, Bahamas, and Cuba 1930s, 86176-128
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:56:30 @ 18 fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 10)
      - Streaming File: 86176-128, flash-flv
Selective Index to Correspondents
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973
May 4, 1942, Jan. 21, 1943
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
Dec. 15, 1933, 1935-1939, Jan. 13, 1941, Nov. 9, 1942, Nov. 12, 1942, Dec. 31, 1942, Jan. 4, 1943
DeKruif, Paul, 1890-1971.
Feb. 3, 1943
Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.
Sept. 11, 1940, Nov. 12, 1940
Farley, James Aloysius, 1888-
July 8, 1938, Nov. 8, 1940, Apr. 21, 1941, Nov. 27, 1942, Dec. 30, 1942, Dec. 28, 1942, Mar. 1, 1943
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
July 10, 1934
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-
Nov. 7, 1940, Jan. 21, 1943
Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-
Nov. 13, 1934, 1936, Apr. 13, 1938, Dec. 5, 1938, May 19, 1941, Dec. 3, 1941, Dec. 30, 1942, Feb. 14, 1943, Mar. 15, 1943, Mar. 29, 1943
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
Oct. 20, 1936, May 26, 1938, Jan. 10, 1940
Murphy, George, 1897-1961.
Nov. 5, 1942, Nov. 23, 1942
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-1949.
Jan. 7, 1937, Nov. 5, 1942, Nov. 16, 1942, Dec. 11, 1942, Dec. 29, 1942, Mar. 11, 1943
Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.
Mar. 12, 1941
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-
Dec. 15, 1942, Jan. 21, 1943
Romney, George W., 1907-
Mar. 20, 1943
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.
May 22, 1941, May 19, 1941, May 6, 1941
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945
Jan. 24, 1940, Nov. 25, 1940, Feb. 4, 1941, Oct. 23, 1942
Scholle, August, 1904-
Dec. 30, 1942
Tufty, Esther Van Wagoner, d. 1986
Undated, May 28, 1941, June 9, 1941, Oct. 9, 1941, Nov. 6, 1942, Jan. 26, 1943, Feb. 3, 1943
Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
June 18, 1941